RG 030, Council of Defense
Connecticut State Library
- Series 1. General
  - 5. Reference file, 1917-1919
    - National Security League (Box 138)
      - Bulletin (Box 138)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 138)
      - [“Patriotism Through Education”] (Box 138)
    - Naturalization (Box 138)
    - Newspapers (Box 139)
      - “Bridgeport Advocate” (Box 139)
      - “Corriere Del Connecticut” (Box 139)
      - “Il Cittadino” (Box 139)
      - News Releases (Box 139)
      - Hemstreet’s Press Clipping Bureau (Box 139)
    - Pamphlets (Box 139)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 139)
      - American library Assoc. (Box 139)
      - “Army Supply Record” - Washington (Box 139)
      - “As Others See Us” - Westcott and Mapes, Consulting, Constructing, etc.. (Box 139)
      - Chautauqua Quarterly (Box 139)
      - “Trumbull Cheer” - Trumbull Electric Manufacturing Co., Plainville (Box 139)
    - Patriotic Plays and Pageants (Box 139)
    - Posters - General (Box 139)
    - Proclamation - Commonwealth of Iowa (Box 139)
    - Public Information - Committee on, Washington DC (Box 139)
    - Red Cross (Box 139)
      - American Red Cross Council (Box 139)
      - Bulletins (Box 139)
    - Rehabilitation (Box 139)
    - Reports (Box 139)
      - Extract from Twelth Annual Report of the Reclamation Service (Box 139)
      - Federal Trade Committee, US Chamber of Commerce (Box 139)
      - School Report - Town of Southington, Conn., 1918 (Box 139)
      - Town of Watertown, Conn., 1917-1918 (Box 139)
    - Safety (Box 139)
      - Suggestions for Safety Training - Bureau of Education (Box 140)
      - National Safety Council (Box 140)
        - Bulletins (Box 140)
        - “Safety News” (Box 140)
        - Weekly Letters (Box 140)
        - Posters - General (Box 140)
        - General (Box 140)
        - Accidents (Box 140)
        - Clothes (Box 140)
        - Diseases (Box 140)
        - Elevators (Box 140)
        - Eyes (Box 140)
        - Feet (Box 140)
        - Fire (Box 140)
        - Hands (Box 140)
        - Ladders (Box 140)
        - Machinery (Box 140)
        - Teeth (Box 140)
        - Yards (Box 140)
    - Schools (Box 140)
      - Evening schools and Extension work - Pittsburg Public Schools, 1916-1917 (Box 140)
      - Military School and the War by William Mather Lewis (Box 140)
      - Public Evening Schools, Courses of Instruction Bridgeport (Box 140)
      - School House as a Community Center - by Margaret Woodrow Wilson (Box 140)
      - “School Life” (Box 140)
    - Slides - Lantern (Box 140)
    - Slides - Miscellaneous (Box 140)
    - Songs - Miscellaneous (Box 140)
    - Speech by Franklyn Lane, Delivered at Hotel Astor New York City (Box 140)
    - Statistics - Circular 30,31,32,34 - Dept. of Interior (Box 140)
    - Trade Secretaries Manufacturers Club - Pennsylvania (Box 140)
    - Vocabulary - for Non-English speakers, Bethlehem Steel Co. (Box 140)
    - War Club, Outline of - Activities for National Factories (Box 140)
    - War Garden Commission, National - Washington, DC (Box 140)
    - War Industries Board (Box 140)
    - War Information - General (Box 140)
    - War Information - Service (Box 140)
    - War Problems of the War - by Harriet N. Bircholdt (Box 140)
    - War Risk Insurance (Box 140)
    - War Risk Insurance Bureau Literature [In a brown wrapper] (Box 140)
    - “What America Has Done in this War,” “What France Has Given to Win the War”, “Mighty First of British Empire” - by Girard (Box 140)
    - War Trade Board (Box 141)
      - General (Box 141)
      - “Trading with the Enemy” (Box 141)
      - Exports - General (Box 141)
      - Imports - General (Box 141)
      - Journal (Box 141)
    - YWCA (Box 141)
      - War Work Bulletin (Box 141)
      - “Association Monthly” (Box 141)
      - Pamphlets - War Work Council (Box 141)
    - YMCA - “Association Men” (Box 141)
    - [War Pamphlets - Insurance, War Aims, Speeches, etc..] (Box 141)
    - “US Official Bulletin” - published by the Committee on Public Information, Washington (Box 141)
    - Committee on Public Information - Washington - Publications (Box 146)
      - List of Publications (Box 146)
      - Pres. Wilson’s Address to Congress, 1917 April 2 (Box 146)
      - Red, White, and Blue Series of Pamphlets No.’s 8,9,10 plus several unnumbered (one pamphlet in German, Italian Polish) (Box 146)
      - War Information Series of Pamphlets - No.’s 1-8,10-16,21 (Box 146)
      - War Trade Board - Bulletins and Pamphlets and War Trash Board Journal (Box 147)
- Series 2. Executive Department
  - 6. Organizational materials, 1917-1919 (Box 148)
    Mimeographed documents: "Report of Committee on Organization...June 6, 1917"; Notes on War Bureaus, July 15, 1918"; "Report on Organization and Activities of State Councils of Defense", June 18, 1917 (by Council of National Defense, Section on Cooperation with States), and "report of the Prudential Committee on Continuance of Activities, Monday, November 25, 1918" (signed by "Budget Committee"). Also, photostat copy of proposed organization chart, mimeographed address lists of council and committee members and local boards and committees (multiple copies), and two copies of the published report of the Council, compiled by Henry M. Wriston and others:
    Report of the Connecticut State Council of Defense, December 1918 (Hartford, 1919 )
    .
  - 7. Budget and finance records, 1917-1919 (Box 149)
    - Financial notes from minutes of the Council of Defence, 1917 May 8-1919 February 3; 1 binder (Box 149)
      Includes subject index.
    - Budget, monthly, 1018 July-1919 January; 1 folder (Box 149)
    - Record of expenditures, 1917 December 1-1918 January 25; 1 folder (Box 149)
    - Record of expenditures, 1918 February-1919 February; 1 binder (Box 149)
  - 8. Smileage book accounts, 1918-1919 (Box 150-151)
    Smileage books, paid for by public contributions, were coupon books given to soldiers to purchase entertainment. Included here are sales and order books, ledger, cash books, bank statements, check books, bills and receipts, and sales and publicity materials.
  - 9. Purchasing Department papers, 1918-1919 (Box 152)
    Fragmentary materials, including correspondence, paid invoices, furniture inventories, etc.
  - 10. Mail Room records, 1917-1919 (Box 152-154)
    Daily work reports, address lists, record of outgoing mail, registered mail receipts and record of incoming mail, etc.
  - 11. Mail Room copies of documents mimeographed and distributed, 1917-1919
    In five groups, arranged numerically or alphabetically by code (unknown) or subject.
    Many are marked with the number of copies distributed.
    - File A, Numbers 10-150 (Box 155)
    - File A, Numbers 170-230 (Box 156)
    - File B, A-M (Box 157)
    - File B, N-Z (Box 158)
    - File C, A-G (Box 159)
    - File C, G-W (Box 160)
    - File D (Box 161)
    - File E, A-G (Box 162)
    - File E, G-Z (Box 163)
  - 12. "Collected materials", 1917-1919 (Box 164)
    This series, like others titled "Collected materials", appears to have been accumulated and filed over a period extending perhaps as late as 1924, although nearly all the papers originated during the war period. The Historical Records Department, begun in the fall of 1918, had the responsibility for "gathering in the files of correspondence and other matter in the possession of the various committees whose work is being wound up." A subject outline was drawn up to guide the collecting and filing (see Wriston, Connecticut State Council of Defense, pp. 90-91). The ambitious plan was not carried out fully, but the War Records Department of the State Library apparently did recieve, maintain and enlarge a substantial body of material resulting from this effort. Lists in record Group 12, Entry VII, 8, throw light on this. In the course of many moves of the collection over the years and as a result of poor storage conditions and neglect, the records became badly disarranged. The segments that have now been found, though probably once part of a single "classified" file, are now associated, so far as possible, with the other papers of the departments to which they refer and from which they came (see below items 19, 20, 32, 36, 37, 42, 43, 59, 63, 64, 70, 72 and 89).
    The "collected materials" include a wide range of items: correspondence, memoranda, directives, minutes, account books, press releases, publications, clippings, photographs, flags, banners, posters, blank forms, letterheads, envelopes, rubber stamps, etc. Many items were acquired in multiple copies, and substantial duplication still exists, both within the "collected materials" and between them and other files. The State Library collated groups of duplicate materials and offered them to other libraries (see RG 12, VII, 3)
- Series 3. Americanization Department
  - 13. Correspondence
    Correspondence between the Department and local officials and agencies (alphabetical by town), United State Government offices, non-governmental agencies and individuals, and agencies in other states.
    - Correspondence with Local Officials and Agencies
      - Andover - New Hartford (Box 165)
      - New Haven - Woodstock (Box 166)
    - Correspondence with other Organizations
      - Connecticut (State) (Box 167)
      - Organizations (Connecticut) (Box 167)
        - Federation of Labor (Box 167)
        - Manufacturer's Assoc. of Connecticut (Box 167)
        - State Chamber of Commerce (Box 167)
        - State Board of Education (Box 167)
        - State Council of Defense (Box 167)
      - Form Letters (Box 167)
      - Americanization Committee (Box 167)
      - Budget Committee (Box 167)
      - Industrial Committee (Box 167)
      - Dept. of Publicity (Box 167)
      - Treasury Dept. (Box 167)
      - Bureau War Exhibits (Box 167)
      - Woman's Division (Box 167)
      - Connecticut State Library (Box 167)
      - Foreign Countries (Box 167)
        - Alaska (Box 167)
        - Hawaii (Box 167)
        - Italy (Box 167)
        - Mexico (Box 167)
      - United States (Box 167)
        - Alabama-New York State (Box 167)
          Includes Washington, D.C.
        - New Mexico-Wyoming (Box 168)
  - 14. Subject file, 1917-1919 (Box 168)
    Correspondence, reports, forms, speeches, press releases, mailing lists, etc.
    - Addresses (Box 168)
      - RM Bissell, Conference, 1918 December 11 (Box 168)
      - Bridgeport Chamber of Commerce (Box 168)
      - R.E. Fagan, Danbury, 1919 March 30 (Box 168)
      - S.H. Holmes, Conference, 1918 December 12 (Box 168)
      - Davis L. Summey, Waterbury (Box 168)
      - Working Men’s Club, Hartford, Conn. (Box 168)
      - Rockville Chamber of Commerce (Box 168)
    - Articles (Box 168)
      - Americanization Though Education (Box 168)
      - Memorandum re Exploitation of Aliens in Conn. with the Draft (Box 168)
      - Pending Americanization Bill (Box 168)
    - Assignments (Box 168)
      - Unfinished - Daniel Radam (Box 168)
    - Banks (Box 168)
      - Russian Consul vs. Stephen Drobofzky, Ansonia (Box 168)
    - Blue Prints (Box 168)
      - Exhibition Space, Charter Oak Park, Connecticut State Council of Defense (Box 168)
    - Bolshevism (Box 168)
    - Bonds (Box 168)
      - Lilienthal, NYC vs. Harry Palko, Ansonia (Box 168)
    - Cards, Survey (Box 168)
    - Complaints (Box 168)
      - Martin Cymerys, Hartford vs. Att’y Stephen A. Macheinski, NYC (Box 168)
      - Anthony Zarnota, Hartford vs. Att’y H. Hunt, Hartford (Box 168)
      - Insurance (Box 168)
        - Russian Brotherhood, Ansonia vs. Nikita Sutkovoy, Ansonia (Box 168)
      - Steam Ship Ticket Agents (Box 168)
        - Zackorobitz vs. Zero (Box 168)
    - Thefts (Box 168)
      - Thefts (Box 168)
        - Zackorobitz vs. Zero (Box 168)
    - Circulars [State Council of Defense] (Box 168)
      - #1,#2,#3,#4,#5 (Box 168)
      - Connecticut's Progress Toward Americanization (Box 168)
      - Americanization Must Include (Box 168)
      - Sent With Form Letters to Clergy (Box 168)
      - Form letters (Box 168)
        - War Bureaus, Circular (Box 168)
    - Conference, Americanization, 1918 December 11-12 (Box 168)
      - Proceedings (Box 168)
      - Resolution (Box 168)
      - Statement re the Conference (Box 168)
      - Programs (Box 168)
      - Luncheon (Box 168)
      - Invitations (Box 168)
      - Newspaper Clippings (Box 168)
      - To Those Invited to the Conference (Box 168)
      - Speeches: (Box 168)
        - H.H. Wheaton - Outline (Box 168)
        - Stanley H. Holmes (Box 168)
      - Questions for Discussion (Box 168)
    - Forms (Box 168)
      - Forms - Misc. (Box 168)
      - Sample Forms - Misc. (Box 168)
      - Questionnaires - Bureau of Education, Dept. of Interior (Box 168)
      - Questionnaires (Box 168)
      - Sample Forms - Housing (Box 168)
    - Form letters (Box 168)
      - To Chairmen of Americanization Committees (Box 168)
      - To Menbers of Americanization Committee (Box 168)
      - To Clergy of Connecticut (Box 168)
      - To Editor (Box 168)
      - To Manufacturers and Industrialists of Hartford (Box 168)
      - Sent by Chairmen (Box 168)
      - War Bureaus (Box 168)
    - Hand Bills (Box 168)
      - Proposed (Box 168)
      - English, Italian, Polish (Box 168)
      - Slovak, French, Hungarian, Yiddish (Box 168)
      - Italian (Box 168)
      - Manchester Evening School (Box 168)
      - Allotment to Towns Having Evening School (Box 168)
      - Form Letters (Box 168)
        - Superintendent of Schools (Box 168)
        - Chairmen, Americanization Committee (Box 168)
    - Immigration (Box 168)
      - Courses of Instructions (Box 168)
      - To the United States from 1899 to 1915 (Box 168)
    - Investigation (Box 168)
      - Steamship ticket agents (Box 168)
      - Report on return on foreigners to Europe (Box 168)
    - Legislation (Box 168)
      - Outline of a proposed bill to establish a Department of Americanization (Box 168)
      - A bill to establish a Department of Americanization (Box 168)
      - Bills - Miscellaneous (Box 168)
      - Circulars - Connecticut Chamber of Congress legislation (Box 168)
      - Legislation - Miscellaneous (Box 168)
      - Some of the reasons why State Americanization work should not be placed under State educational authorities (Box 168)
      - Brief in favor of Senate Bills Nos. 366 & 363 (Box 168)
    - Letterheads (Box 168)
      - General (Box 168)
    - Lists (Box 168)
      - Committees on education & appropriation (Box 168)
      - Persons invited to hearing and subjects to be discussed (Box 168)
      - Senators & representatives connected with War Bureaus or Americanization Committees (Box 168)
      - Members, Educational Committee (Box 168)
      - Jewish organizations - Hartford (Box 168)
      - Those pledging to attend night school (Box 168)
      - Membership, Polish National Alliance Society, Hartford, Conn. (Box 168)
      - Agencies requesting Connecticut Council of Defense to place them on mailing list (Box 168)
      - Chairmen, Americanization Committees (Box 168)
      - Banks in Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Books on immigration (Box 168)
      - Catholic clergy in Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Cities having evening schools, U.S. (Box 168)
      - Chairmen, Americanization Committees in towns having evening schools (Box 168)
      - Chairmen, Americanization Committees, State Councils of Defense (Box 168)
      - Chairmen, Local women's committees, State Council of Defense (Box 168)
      - Chambers of Commerce (Box 168)
      - Committees on Americanization (Box 168)
      - Connecticut State Council of Defense (Box 168)
      - District, Town and City Superintendents (Box 168)
      - Evening schools (Box 168)
      - Foreign language speakers for Liberty Loan Campaign (Box 168)
      - Industries from Chamber of Commerce Bulletins interested in Americanization (Box 168)
      - Foreign language newspapers published (Box 168)
      - Foreign speakers from war rallies (Box 168)
      - American Loyalty Commission. Com. on Foreign Born, Connecticut State Council of Defense (Box 168)
      - Hungarian leaders (Box 168)
      - Italian leaders (Box 168)
      - Italian societies (Box 168)
      - Invited - Americanization Meeting New Haven War Bureau (Box 168)
      - Liberty Choruses of Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Connecticut Americanizer (Box 168)
      - Motion Picture Theatres in Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Persons attending luncheon of Savings" Banks Association of Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Persons interested in Americanization (Box 168)
      - Mailing list of Schedule No. 4 (Box 168)
      - Racial organizations (Box 168)
      - Subsidiary companies of United States Rubber Co. (Box 168)
      - Towns having evening schools, Connecticut (Box 168)
      - Members, House and Senate, Connecticut, 1919 (Box 168)
      - Superintendent in towns having evening schools (Box 168)
      - Americanization chairmen, Women's Committee, Connecticut Council of Defense (Box 168)
      - War Bureaus having Americanization Committees (Box 168)
      - War Bureaus, Connecticut State Council of Defense (Box 168)
    - Minutes (Box 169)
      - Committee on Americanization (Box 169)
      - Executive Committee meeting (Box 169)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 169)
      - General - Pertaining to Americanization (Box 169)
      - General (Box 169)
    - News releases (Box 169)
      - Connecticut Americanizer Institution of paper, News release #1 (Box 169)
      - Mrs. Arnold's Story, News release #2 (Box 169)
      - Establishment of local committees, News release #3 (Box 169)
      - Progress of night schools, News release #4 (Box 169)
      - Machinery of Americanization Department, News release #5 (Box 169)
      - Pay envelope slips & handbills, News release #6 (Box 169)
      - Request for aid of clergy, News release #7 (Box 169)
      - History of Americanization in Connecticut, News release #8 (Box 169)
      - Miner's Propaganda, News release #9 (Box 169)
      - Library Schedule, News release #10 (Box 169)
      - Exploitation of Foreign-born, News release #11 (Box 169)
      - News releases - Miscellaneous (Box 169)
    - Order of Business (Box 169)
    - Pamphlets (Box 169)
      - A Family Letter, The Atlantic Monthly, 1917 December (Box 169)
      - Help the Alien to Understand (Box 169)
      - What You Can Do for Americanism (Box 169)
      - Attention! (in Polish, English, Italian) (Box 169)
      - Attention! (in Slovak, Hungarian, Yiddish, French) (Box 169)
      - Think This Over (Box 169)
    - Pay Envelope Slips (Box 169)
      - Form Letters (Box 169)
        - Superintendent of Schools (Box 169)
        - Chairmen, Americanization Committee (Box 169)
    - Plans (Box 169)
      - Americanization plan for industries (Box 169)
      - Americanization plan for local communities (Box 169)
      - Department organizations (Box 169)
      - Organizations (Box 169)
      - Outline of suggestions, Manchester War Bureau (Box 169)
      - State Campaign of Americanization (Box 169)
      - Allotment of pay envelope slips (Box 169)
      - Form Letters (Box 169)
        - Chairmen, Americanization Committee, Plan for local communities (Box 169)
    - Posters (Box 169)
      - English (Box 169)
      - Hungarian & Yiddish (Box 169)
      - Italian (Box 169)
      - Lithuanian & Bohemian (Box 169)
      - Polish (Box 169)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 169)
      - Bids on posters (Box 169)
      - Distribution (Box 169)
        - Apportioned distribution of posters (Box 169)
        - Distribution of posters (Box 169)
      - Form Letters (Box 169)
        - To Chiefs of Police Departments (Box 169)
        - To School Superintendents (Box 169)
        - To Town Clerks (Box 169)
        - To War Bureaus (Box 169)
        - Memoranda Regarding School Posters (Box 169)
    - Proclamations (Box 169)
      - A Proclamation, Governor Holcumb (Box 169)
    - Publications (Box 169)
      - Connecticut Americanizer (Box 169)
    - Purpose & Aims (Box 169)
    - Reports (Box 169)
      - Reports (Box 169)
      - Department of Americanization (Box 169)
      - Americanization Department, State Council of Defense (Box 169)
      - Annual Report, 1918 November; 3 folders (Box 169)
      - Evening school reports (Box 169)
      - H.R. Branche, Field Assistant (Box 169)
      - Accomplishments of Department of Americanization, 1918 October 28 (Box 169)
    - Requisitions (Box 169)
      - #1, #2, #3, #4 (Box 169)
      - #5, How Public Libraries Can Carry on Americanization Work (Box 169)
      - #13 (Box 169)
      - Schedule of assignments (Box 169)
      - Schedules of operation sent out (Box 169)
      - List of Schedules of operation, Americanization Department (Box 169)
      - Form Letters (Box 169)
        - Chambers of Commerce (Box 169)
        - To Chairmen of Americanization Committee (Box 169)
        - Industries (Box 169)
        - To Librarians (Box 169)
        - School Authorities (Box 169)
        - War Bureaus (Box 169)
      - Follow-up Letters (Box 169)
        - War Bureaus (Box 169)
    - Slogans (Box 169)
      - Suggested (Box 169)
    - Statements (Box 169)
      - Statements for Connecticut Bulletin (Box 169)
      - Statement regarding Americanization Activities of Federal Department (Box 169)
      - Statement regarding the Necessity of Continuing Activities of Department of Americanization (Box 169)
      - List of Foreign -born males, 16 years and over, in Connecticut. Taken from the Military Census (Box 169)
        - 1917 March (Box 169)
    - Statistics (Box 169)
      - Bridgeport, 2 folders (Box 169)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 169)
      - Connecticut, 1910 (Box 169)
      - Americanization Activities in Connecticut as Compared with other states (Box 169)
    - Telegrams (Box 169)
    - Translations (Box 169)
  - 15. Papers of Director, H. H. Wheaton, 1918-1919 (Box 171)
    Correspondence (mostly outgoing) and other papers from the desk of the Director of the Americanization Department.
    Letters from May Townsend Seymour of Hartford, her handwritten report of the Circle for Negro war Relief, Unit 16 in Hartford, NAACP enclosures and newspaper clippings were removed on January 4, 2000 and put into Restricted Access. Photocopies put in Box 170.
  - 16. Historical material, 1918-1919 (Box 171)
    Papers relevant to the history of the Department, evidently collected from other files for use in preparing the published history of the Council of Defense.
  - 17. Budget and related papers, 1918-1919 (Box 171)
    Monthly budget and payroll statements, requisitions and statement of expenditures.
  - 18. Lists of aliens and related material, 1918-1919
    Lists of aliens, by nation of origin, with related correspondence and other records.
    - Lists, 3 folders (Box 172)
      Concerning Parent Teachers Association of aliens exempted by local boards of influential naturalized citizens sent by town chairmen
    - Letters (Box 172)
      Town chairmen and Parent Teachers Association material.
    - Lists of aliens
      - German-Americans in Connecticut (Box 173)
      - Danish and Italians (Box 173)
      - Canadian, Welsh, Indian, Irish, Scotch (Box 173)
      - German (Box 173)
      - Austrian and German (Box 173)
      - Polish (Box 174)
      - Italian (Box 174)
      - Russian (Box 174)
      - Swedish (Box 174)
  - 19. "Collected materials", 1917-1919 (Box 175)
    See note for Item 12 above.
- Series 4. Child Welfare Department
  - 20. "Collected materials", 1917-1919 (Box 176)
- Series 5. Food Supply Department
  - 21. Food Supply Department
    - H. Food Supply & Conservation (Box 177)
      - H01: Organization (Box 177)
      - H03: Legislation, 2 folders (Box 177)
      - H04: Activities (Box 177)
      - H05: Publications - bulletins, etc. (Box 177)
        - H05: Weekly newsletters (Box 177)
      - H06: Meetings, conferences, programs, etc. (Box 177)